Finding Aid for Hyde & Bobbio records, 1909-1967
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hyde & Bobbio records 1909-1967, 1925-1967
Hyde & Bobbio (Firm)
54 tubes
7 linear feet
2010016 Bb 2
Detroit based mechanical engineers who worked with prominent architects on residential and commercial buildings throughout Michigan; project files.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in 2009 by Thomas W. Brunk (donor no. 8193 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Eric F. Hyde established his mechanical engineering practice in the late 1920s, specializing in heating and cooling systems. During the practice's first few years, it was located at 620 Detroit Savings Bank. However, by 1935, Hyde had relocated to 509 Free Press Building. Hyde worked with prominent architects on residential and commercial buildings throughout Michigan, including his father, Detroit based architect Arthur Hyde. By the late 1940s, Hyde had partnered with mechanical engineer Joseph S. Bobbio and the practice was changed from Eric F. Hyde, Mechanical Engineer to Hyde & Bobbio, Inc. The practice remained active well into the late 1960s.
Architects represented in the collection include among others Henry Booth, C. Howard Crane, J. Ivan Dise, Clair Ditchy, Alden B. Dow, Wallace Frost, Arthur Hyde, Albert Kahn, Hugh T. Keyes, Malcomson & Higginbotham, Richard Marr, George Mason, Smith, Hinchman, & Grylls, William B. Stratton, Clarence J. Whitney.
The Hyde & Bobbio, Inc. records are organized into two series: Project Files and Other Files. The collection encompasses seven linear feet of correspondence, mechanical specifications, data sheets, project accounts, and folded architectural drawings, as well as rolled architectural drawings in fifty-four tubes.
Subjects:
Architecture--Michigan.; Bobbio, Joseph.; Booth, Henry Scripps, 1897-1988; Crane, C. Howard (Charles Howard), 1885-1952.; Dise, J. Ivan (Joseph Ivan); Ditchy, Clair W. (Clair William); Dow, Alden B., 1904-1983; Dwellings--Michigan.; Frost, Wallace, 1892-1962.; Higginbotham, William E.; Hyde, Arthur K. (Arthur Knox); Hyde & Bobbio (Firm); Hyde, Eric C.; Kahn, Albert, 1869-1942.; Keyes, Hugh T. (Hugh Tallman); Malcomson, William G., 1853-1937.; Marr, Richard H.; Mason, George D., b. 1856.; Mechanical engineers--Michigan--Detroit.; Smith, Hinchman, and Grylls, inc.; Stratton, William B.; Whitney, Clarence J.
Genre Terms:
Architectural drawings (visual works)--Michigan.
- Project Files
  The series Project Files contains material related to the architectural jobs worked on by Eric F. Hyde, Mechanical Engineer and later Hyde & Bobbio, Inc. The projects have been arranged by job number, except for the first four projects, which do not contain a job number. Job Numbers 119 to 631 are projects undertaken by the practice when it was only Eric F. Hyde. Job Numbers 48-69 to 67-11 represent projects undertaken by the practice after the addition of Joseph S. Bobbio. When available, the project's architect and location have been provided. The project files contain architectural drawings supplemented with paper records. The paper records consist of correspondence between Hyde or Bobbio and the projects' architects, mechanical specifications, data sheets, and project accounts. In many instances, only architectural drawings remain and in some instances, only paper records remain. The majority of the drawings are blueprints but there is a small number of ink on linen architectural drawings. Architectural drawings include both folded drawings and rolled drawings. Folded drawings can be found in the project files and the rolled drawings can be found in tubes. The tubes contain only architectural drawings.
  There are many instances when drawings predate Eric F. Hyde's mechanical engineering practice. The reason for this is Hyde or Bobbio were sometimes brought in during a building's renovation and were provided with the original plans for that building. For example, Hyde worked on the Veterans' Club in Detroit (job number 147). However, since the Veteran's Club occupied the former Detroit Museum of Art, the project files contain the floor plans of the former Museum. Another example is the store building for the Paterson Development Corporation (job number 152). In the late 1920s, the building was renovated under the guidance of architects Stratton & Hyde. However, architect George Mason originally designed the building in 1909. As a result, the project file for this project contains the original George Mason blueprints from 1909.
  - David Stott Building, 1150 Griswold Street, Detroit, architects Donaldson & Meier 1928 (Tube 1)
  - Harpers Hospital, Detroit, architects Malcomson & Higginbotham 1916 (Tube 2)
  - Theater, Store and Office for Hugh Scherer, Grand River and Fourteenth, Detroit, architect Howard C. Crane undated (Tube 3)
  - University Club, Detroit, architects Smith, Hinchman, & Grylls 1930 (Tube 4)
  - University Club, Detroit, architects Smith, Hinchman, & Grylls 1930 (Tube 5)
    (continued)
  - # 119, Receiving Hospital, architects Carey & Esselstyn 1925 (Tube 6)
  - # 121, Julian P. Bowen Residence, 16628 Jefferson Avenue, Grosse Pointe Park, architect Wallace Frost 1926 (Tube 7)
  - # 123, Forest Lake Country Club, Bloomfield Hills, architect Wallace Frost 1926 (Tube 8)
  - # 127, Jerome E. Keane Residence, 379 Lakeland Avenue, Grosse Pointe Village, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1925 (Tube 9)
  - # 129, Embassy Club Building, southwest corner of Second and Temple avenues, Detroit, architects Halpin & Jewel 1928 (Tube 10)
  - # 133, Dr. H. Lee Simpson Residence and Garage, 2494 Iroquois Avenue, Detroit, architects Stratton & Hyde 1928 (Tube 11)
  - # 134, William Hendrie Residence and Garage, 120 Provencal Road, Grosse Pointe Farms, architect Hugh T. Keyes
    - Project Records 1927 (Box 1)
    - Architectural Drawings 1927 (Tube 12)
  - # 136, Trenton Municipal Building, northwest corner of Washington and Maple Street, Trenton, architect Hugh T. Keyes
    - Project Records 1927 (Box 1)
      (includes blueprints)
    - Architectural Drawings 1927 (Tube 13)
  - # 137, Morse Rohnert Residence, 820 Edgemont Park, Grosse Pointe Park, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1927 (Tube 14)
  - # 139, Roscoe B. Jackson Residence, Bloomfield Township 1925 (Tube 15)
  - # 145, William B. Stratton Residence, 938 Three Mile Drive, Grosse Pointe Park, architects Stratton & Hyde 1927 (Box 1)
  - # 147, Veterans' Club (formerly The Detroit Museum of Art, Jefferson Avenue, Detroit undated (Tube 16)
    (drawings include floor plans of the old Detroit Museum of Art)
  - # 152, Paterson Development Corporation, Store Building and Residential Alterations, northwest corner of Jefferson and Van Dyke, Detroit, architects Stratton & Hyde 1928 (Box 1)
    (includes George Mason blueprints, 1909)
  - # 155, Hugh McMillan Residence, Grosse Pointe, architect Hugh T. Keyes
    - Project Records 1928 (Box 1)
    - Architectural Drawings 1928 (Tube 17)
  - # 164, Mrs. F. E. Currah Residence, Victoria Avenue, Windsor, Ontario, architect Frank S. Carson 1928 (Tube 18)
  - # 168, Maurice Goldenberg Residence and Garage, Wellesley Drive, Palmer Woods, Detroit, architect Wallace Frost 1928 (Tube 19)
  - # 171, Earle B. Wilson Residence and Garage, Lincoln Avenue and Shirley Drive, Birmingham, architect Clarence J. Whitney undated (Tube 20)
  - # 172, Women's City Club, Park Avenue, Detroit, original 1923 architects Stratton & Snyder, 1929-1931 (Box 1)
  - # 174, Mrs. Francis T. Dwyer Residence, 78 Lake Shore Road, Grosse Pointe Farms, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1928 (Tube 21)
  - # 181, Mrs. Burns Henry Residence and Garage, Provencal Road, Grosse Pointe Farms, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1928 (Box 1)
  - # 182, Cleveland Thurber Residence, 26 Kenwood Road, Grosse Pointe Farms, architect J. Ivan Dise
    - Project Records 1928 (Box 1)
    - Architectural Drawings 1928 (Tube 22)
  - # 183, William Harris, Jr. Residence, additions and alterations, 15410Windmill Pointe, Grosse Pointe Park, architect Hugh T. Keyes (Box 1)
    - Project Records 1929, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Architectural Drawings 1929 (Tube 23)
  - # 187, Ross W. Judson Residence, 15324 Windmill Pointe Drive, Grosse Pointe, architect Wallace Frost 1928 (Tube 24)
  - # 193, Wimbleton Terrace for Bloomfield Investment Company, southwest corner of Adams and Wimbleton Drive, architect Wallace Frost 1928 (Tube 25)
  - # 194, Wallace J. Frost Office Workroom, Birmingham, architect Wallace J. Frost 1928 (Box 1)
  - # 195, Henry Philips William Residence, 180 Provencal Road, Grosse Pointe Farms, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1928 (Box 1)
  - # 196, Detroit Savings Bank Branch, Detroit, architect Albert Kahn 1919 (Tube 26)
  - # 198, William P. Stevens Residence Additions, 421 Lake Shore Road, Grosse Pointe Farms, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1929-1930 (Tube 27)
  - # 199, Bloomfield Hills Children's School, additions, Cranbrook, Cranbrook Architectural Office, architect Henry Booth
    - Project Records 1929 (Box 1)
    - Architectural Drawings 1929 (Tube 28)
  - # 212, Hugh T. Keyes Residence, Forest Hills Subdivision, Birmingham, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1929 (Tube 29)
  - # 215, Lewis A. Garred Residence, Merriweather Road, Grosse Pointe Farms, architects Stratton & Hyde 1929 (Tube 30)
  - # 219, Henry L. Caulkins Residence Addition, 102 Lewiston Road, Grosse Pointe Farms, architects Stratton & Hyde 1929 (Tube 31)
  - # 220, Apartment Building for Harmon Apartment Company, Harmonie Avenue, Birmingham, architect Wallace Frost 1929 (Tube 32)
  - # 221, William A. Black Residence and Garage, Canterbury Road, Sherwood Forest, Detroit, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1929 (Box 1)
  - # 222, Gilbert W. Lee Residence and Garage, 143 Lake Shore Road, Grosse Pointe Farms, architect Hugh T. Keyes
    - Project Records 1930 (Box 1)
      (includes blue line prints)
    - Architectural Drawings 1930 (Tube 33)
  - # 228, Michigan Naval Armory, alterations and additions, Detroit, architect Arthur K. Hyde 1935 (Box 1)
  - # 230, J. Walter Drake Residence and Garage, Windmill Pointe, Grosse Pointe Park, architect J. Ivan Dise 1929 (Tube 34)
  - # 231, Floyd Taylor Residence and Garage, Timberlake Drive, Bloomfield Hills, architect J. Ivan Dise 1929 (Tube 35)
  - # 248, Edsel B. Ford Cottage, Gaukler Pointe, architect Albert Kahn 1929 (Tube 36)
  - # 250, Donovan Building, Grand River and Oakman Boulevard, Detroit, architects O'Dell & Diehl 1929 (Tube 37)
  - # 292, L. Prentis Residence, Balmoral Drive, Palmer Woods, Detroit, architect Richard H. Marr 1930 (Tube 38)
  - # 297, E.S. Bennett Residence, Country Club Lane, Grosse Pointe Farms, architects Stratton and Hyde 1930 (Box 1)
  - # 299, K.C. McRae Residence, Detroit, architect Hugh Keyes 1930 (Box 1)
  - # 315, White Star Refining, three story addition to the administration building, West Grand Boulevard, Detroit, architects Stratton and Hyde 1930 (Box 1)
  - # 326, Gail Stevens Hunting Lodge, Metamora, architect Hugh T. Keyes
    - Project Records 1931 (Box 1)
    - Architectural Drawings 1931 (Tube 39)
  - # 342, Bohn Residence, 415 Brainard Street, Detroit, architect Richard H. Marr 1933 (Box 2)
  - # 362, Taylor Center School, Taylor Center, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1933 (Box 2)
  - # 364, National Twist Drill and Tool Company, alterations to office, 6522 Brush Street, Detroit, architect Richard H. Marr 1934 (Box 2)
  - # 378, Tower Movie Theater, architect C. Easton Allen
    - Project Records 1935 (Box 2)
    - Architectural Drawings 1935 (Tube 40)
  - # 385, Bruce MacDonald Store, Flint, architects Woodworth & Loree 1934 (Tube 41)
  - # 398, J. Tracy Residence, architects Woodworth & Loree 1935-1939, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - # 399, Canfield Summer Home, Frankfort, architects Woodworth and Loree
    - Project Records 1935 (Box 2)
    - Architectural Drawings 1935 (Tube 42)
  - # 400, R. Sherlock Residence, 2025 Vinewood Blvd, Ann Arbor, architects Woodworth and Loree 1935-1937 (Box 2)
  - # 401, Tuttle and Clark, 1533 Woodward Avenue, Detroit 1935 (Box 2)
  - # 411, Our Lady of the Rosary School, Harper and Woodward Avenue, Detroit, architect Clair W. Ditchy 1935 (Box 2)
  - # 429, Milan Prison, Milan, architects Woodworth & Loree
    - Project Records 1933-1934, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Architectural Drawings 1933-1934 (Tube 43)
  - # 448, Trumull Residence, 415 Brainard Street, Detroit, architect Richard Marr undated (Tube 44)
  - # 467, Henry Hubbard Residence, Grosse Pointe Farms, architect Arthur Hyde 1935 (Box 2)
  - # 478, L.R. Hunter Residence, Additions and Alterations, Ann Arbor, architects Woodworth and Loree 1936-1938 (Box 2)
  - # 478, Hunter Residence Additions and Alterations, Ann Arbor, architects Woodworth & Loree 1936 (Tube 45)
  - # 481, G.W. Linton Residence, Lahser & 13 Mile Roads, architect Clair W. Ditchy (Box 2)
    - Project Records 1932-1936 (Box 2)
    - Architectural Drawings 1932 (Tube 46)
  - # 483, Warfield Theater, electrical work, Detroit, architect C. Easton Allen 1936, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - # 488, L.H. Buhs Residence, Lochmoor Drive near Lakeshore Drive, Grosse Pointe Shores, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1936 (Box 3)
  - # 489, C.E. Ustick Residence, Birmingham, MI, architect W.D. Knox 1936-1937 (Box 3)
  - # 502, Harry E. Martin Residence, Detroit, architect Arthur K. Hyde
    - Project Records 1936, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Architectural Drawings 1936 (Tube 47)
  - # 513, John Owen Residence, Country Home, Metamora, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1936 (Box 3)
  - # 514, First Presbyterian Church, Plymouth, architect Thomas W. Moss 1936, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - # 519, Dr. B.M. Patten Residence, Highland Road at Concord Road, Ann Arbor, architects Woodworth & Loree 1936 (Box 3)
  - # 519, Patten Residence, Highland Road at Concord Road, Ann Arbor 1936 (Tube 48)
  - # 521, Max Gilman Residence, 312 Lake Park Road, Birmingham, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1936-1937, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - # 530, Martin Haller Company Store, Ann Arbor, architects Woodworth & Loree 1936 (Box 3)
  - # 532, Donald McPhail Residence, Pemberton Road near Essex, Grosse Pointe, architects Hyde & Williams 1936 (Box 3)
  - # 533, William Theodore Jones Residence, Lot #18, Detroit Gulf Club, architect Richard H. Marr
    - Project Records 1937 (Box 3)
    - Architectural Drawings 1937 (Tube 49)
  - # 547, Women's Hospital, 432 E. Hancock Avenue, Detroit, architect Albert Kahn 1937 (Box 3)
  - # 548, Dr. Sydney H. Morgan Residence, Lakeland Road, Grosse Pointe, architects Hyde & Williams 1937 (Box 3)
  - # 550, Miss Bessie McCoy Residence, Greenview Boulevard, Detroit, architect Hyde & Williams 1937 (Box 3)
  - # 554, C.L. Miller Residence, Pilgrim Road, Birmingham, architect Frank Chapmen 1936 (Tube 50)
  - # 561, Whaling Store, Alterations and additions, 615-617 Woodward Avenue, Detroit, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1937 (Box 3)
  - # 570, Hughes & Hatcher Store, 2305 Woodward Avenue, Detroit
    - Project Records 1937 (Box 4)
    - Architectural Drawings 1937 (Tube 51)
  - # 572, George M. Gaston Residence, Detroit, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1938 (Box 4)
  - # 578, Republic Steel Corporation, Cleveland, Ohio, architect Albert Kahn
    - Project Records 1937 (Box 4)
    - Architectural Drawings 1937 (Tube 52)
    - Architectural Drawings 1937 (Tube 53)
  - # 601, St. Cyprian's Church, Detroit, architects Lancelot Sukert
    - Project Records 1938 (Box 4)
    - Architectural Drawings 1938 (Tube 54)
  - # 623, Philco Radio & Television Corporation, 2778 East Grand Boulevard, Detroit, architect H.D. Ilgenfritz
    - Project Records 1937 (Box 4)
    - Architectural Drawings 1937 (Tube 55)
  - # 631, John Owen Residence, Stephens Road between Kercheval Avenue and Ridge Road, Grosse Pointe Farms, architect Hugh Keyes 1938 (Box 4)
  - # 48-69, Macauley Whiting House, Midland, architect Alden B. Dow 1948, 2 folders (Box 4)
    (includes blue-line prints)
  - # 48-74, Sidney T. Miller, Jr. Residence, Irving Lane, Grosse Pointe Farms 1948 (Box 4)
  - # 48-79, Julian P. Bowen Residence, Grosse Pointe Farms, architect Wallace Frost 1949 (Box 4)
  - # 49-75, Emory Ford Residence, 2 Woodlawn Place, Grosse Pointe, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1949 (Box 4)
    (includes blue-line print)
  - # 50-14, Dr. Sibley Hoobler Residence, Ann Arbor, architect Alden B. Dow 1950, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - # 50-66, Robert S. Ballmer House, Midland, architect Alden B. Dow 1950 (Box 5)
  - # 50-134, George Duffy House, Port Huron, architect Alden B. Dow 1951 (Box 5)
  - # 51-34, R.B. Bennet Residence, Midland, architect Alden B. Dow 1951 (Box 5)
  - # 52-22, Bert L. Smokler Residence, 1900 Balmoral Drive, Detroit, architect Hugh T. Keyes 1952 (Box 5)
  - # 52-33, Edgar R. Siebert, Bretton Drive and Huntington, Detroit, architect F. Burr Joslin 1952-1954, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - # 53-78, Grosse Pointe Congregational Church, 240 Chalfonte Ave, Grosse Pointe Farms, architect George Mason & Co. 1947-1948 (Tube 56)
  - # 54-24, Robert J. Davis Residence, Lake Shore Lane, Grosse Pointe Woods, architect Robert J. Davis 1954 (Box 5)
  - # 54-35, J.L. Sherk House, Midland, architect Alden B. Dow 1954 (Box 5)
  - # 54-48, Eero Saarinen Residence, Bloomfield Hills, architect Alden B. Dow 1954 (Box 5)
  - # 55-01, Dr. R.C. Birmingham House, Adrian, architect Alden B. Dow 1955, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - # 55-08, Detroit Athletic Club, architects Marr and Marr, Detroit 1944, 1955 (Box 5)
  - # 55-81, Detroit Boat Club, Belle Isle, Detroit, architect Earl G. Meyer 1956, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - # 57-22, Detroit Institute of Art, Alterations to Rivera Court, Detroit, architects Pilafian and Suron 1958, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - # 58-43, Benson Ford Residence, 635 Lake Shore Drive, Grosse Pointe Shores, architect Hugh T. Keyes (Box 6)
  - # 61-59, Hebert H. Dow House, Additions, 2301 West Sugnet, Midland, architect Alden B. Dow 1961-1962 (Box 6)
  - # 61-63, John Riecker House, architect Alden B. Dow 1961 (Box 6)
  - # 63-53, University of Michigan Botanical Gardens, Ann Arbor, architect Alden B. Dow 1963 (Box 6)
  - # 64-09, Lynn A. Townsend House, Bloomfield Hills, architect Alden B. Dow 1964, 3 folders (Box 7)
    (includes blueprints and blue-line prints)
  - # 67-11, Michael L. Dow Residence, East Lansing, architect Alden B. Dow 1967 (Box 7)
- Other files
  The series Other Files contains a job list and the professional files of Eric Hyde. The job list is incomplete and refers only to the projects undertaken by Eric Hyde and not by Hyde & Bobbio, Inc. The professional files contain Eric Hyde's non-project related correspondence.
  - Job List (Box 7)
  - Eric Hyde, Professional Files
    - 1948 (Box 7)
    - 1949 (Box 7)
    - 1952 (Box 7)